William Anthony
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
William Anthony papers
1956-2003
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
William Anthony
1.5 linear feet
The papers of contemporary painter and author William Anthony measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1956 to 2003. Found within the papers are scattered biographical materials; correspondence files; exhibition files; original art work; files of reproductions of his art work; a file for his book A New Approach to Figure Drawing; clippings; photographs; a recorded lecture and announcements of Anthony's slide talks.
Biographical Note
American painter William Graham Anthony was born on September 25, 1934 in Fort Monmouth, New Jersey. While majoring in history at Yale University, Anthony attended a few art courses, one of which was taught by Josef Albers. He also attended the Art Students' League in 1958 and 1961.
After graduating from Yale, he joined his family in California, where he attended the San Francisco Art Institute. In 1962, Anthony taught figure drawing at a commercial art school in San Francisco, where he developed a method of drawing that resulted in his book A New Approach to Figure Drawing. Two years later he moved to New York City.
From 1977 to 1978, Anthony made a series of drawings for magazine Andy Warhol's Interview, and published another book Bible Stories. In 1983, he married Norma Neuman, and continued to produce and exhibit his art work, including solo exhibitions in New York, California, and Europe. In 1988, the Jargon Society published an additional book, Bill Anthony's Greatest Hits. Anthony also teaches painting to senior citizens.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of contemporary painter and author William Anthony measure 1.5 linear feet and date from 1956 to 2003. Found within the papers are scattered biographical materials; correspondence files; exhibition files; original art work; files of reproductions of his art work; a file for his book A New Approach to Figure Drawing; clippings; photographs; a recorded lecture and announcements of Anthony's slide talks. This material offers a comprehensive record of the works and exhibitions of this prolific painter.
Arrangement
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1976-2001 (Box 1; 2 folders; Reel 5875)
Series 2: Correspondence Files, 1961-2001 (Box 1; 16 folders; Reel 5875)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1961-2003 (Box 1, OV 3; 32 folders; Reel 5875)
Series 4: Art work, 1961-2003 (Box 1, OV 3; 6 folders; Reel 5875)
Series 5: Reproductions of Art Work Created in 1976-2003, undated (Box 1, 2; 25 folders; Reels 5875-5877)
Series 6: File for Book, A New Approach to Figure Drawing, 1965 (Box 2; 2 folders; Reel 5877)
Series 7: Clippings, 1956-2002, undated (Box 2; 2 folders; Reel 5877)
Series 8: Photographs, 1965-2000, undated (Box 2; 3 folders; Reel 5877)
Series 9: Recorded Lecture and Announcements of Slide Talks, 1985-1990, undated (Box 2; 1 folder; Reel 5877 and unfilmed)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Names" when they are creators or contributors and under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents.
Subjects-Topical:
Painting, American -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Drawings
Names:
Johns, Jasper, 1930-; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-; Ross, David A., 1949-; Carpenter, Charles Hope, 1916-; Little, Carl; Masheck, Joseph; Schwabsky, Barry; Rosenblum, Robert
Provenance
The William Anthony papers were donated by Anthony from 2001 to 2003. In 1976, he lent miscellaneous photocopied material for microfilming. The loaned materials do not duplicate the later gifts except for single letters from Jasper Johns (1972), William King, Claes Oldenburg, Theodoros Stamos, and a book endorsement comment signed by Larry Rivers. [Note: Reel 1094 is not described in this finding aid.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on microfilm Reels 5875-5877. Earlier loaned material is also available on Reel 1094. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1976-2001, Series 1:; (Box 1; 2 folders; Reel 5875)
  Biographical material consists primarily of biographical accounts that include listings of Anthony's exhibitions. The chronology provides more detailed information concerning events in Anthony's life.
  - Biographical Accounts, 1981-2001 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Chronology, 1976-2001 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
- Correspondence Files, 1961-2001, Series 2:; (Box 1; 16 folders; Reel 5875)
  Correspondence consists primarily of alphabetically-arranged folders of letters from colleagues who maintained a long-term contact with Anthony. Single letters from other colleagues have been placed in a separate alphabetical arrangement and filed in miscellaneous correspondence and includes letters from Jules Feiffer, William King, Alfred Leslie, Sol Lewitt, Claes Oldenburg, Harold Rosenberg, and Theodoros Stamos.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1961-2001, (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Charles Carpenter, 1979-2001 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - James Duffy, Jr., 1975-1998 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Jasper Johns, 1972-2000 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Roy Lichtenstein, 1977-2000 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Carl Little, 1989-2000 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Joe Masheck, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Robert Rosenblum, 1981-2000 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - David Ross, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Barry Schwabsky, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Leo Steinberg, 1981-2001 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Jonathan Williams, 1972-2000, (3 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5875)
- Exhibition Files, 1961-2003, Series 3:; (Box 1, OV 3; 32 folders; Reel 5875)
  Exhibition files primarily contain printed material concerning exhibitions of Anthony's work. Some files also contain letters, price lists, and photographs. The file for the Cokkie Snoei Gallery of Rotterdam contains an original drawing for the exhibition announcement. There is also a file for an exhibition of other artist's works owned and exhibited by Anthony.
  - Exhibition Files for Exhibitions of Anthony's Work, 1961-2003, (32 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Exhibition Files for Exhibitions of Other Artist's Works Owned by Anthony, 1997 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Four oversize posters for Now Gallery, New York, 1985-1987 (Box OV 3, Reel 5875)
  - Oversize poster and a duplicate for the Robert Berman Gallery, Santa Monica, California, 1998 (Box OV 3, Reel 5875)
- Art work, 1961-2003, Series 4:; (Box 1, OV 3; 6 folders; Reel 5875)
  Artwork primarily consists of pencil drawings, but also includes 2 tempera sketches and a silkscreen line self-portrait.
  - Drawings, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Drawings, tempera paintings, and silkscreen, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Drawings, 1971-2003, (4 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5875)
  - Eleven oversize drawings, 1971-2000 (Box OV 3, Reel 5875)
- Reproductions of Art Work Created in 1976-2003, undated, Series 5:; (Box 1, 2; 25 Folders; Reels 5875-5877)
  Files of photocopies and photographs of Anthony's drawings and paintings created from 1976 to 2003 offer a comprehensive overview of his work.
  - Reproductions of Art Work Created in 1976-1995, (17 folders) (Box 1, Reel 5875-5876)
  - Reproductions of Art Work Created in 1996-2003, (8 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5876-5877)
- File for Book, A New Approach to Figure Drawing, 1965, Series 6:; (Box 2; 2 folders)
  A file concerning Anthony's book, A New Approach to Figure Drawing, contains letters, printed material, and original art work. Also included is an endorsement comment signed by Larry Rivers.
  - File for A New Approach to Figure Drawing, 1965 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5877)
- Clippings, 1956-2002, undated, Series 7:; (Box 2; 2 folders)
  Clippings consist of cartoons, articles about Anthony, and a copy of Public Illumination Magazine.
  - Clippings, 1956-2002, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5877)
- Photographs, 1965-2000, undated, Series 8:; (Box 2; 3 folders)
  The majority of photographs are of Anthony and of his students and colleagues, including Dore Ashton. Four photographs are photocopies.
  - Photographs of Anthony's parents, undated (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5877)
  - Photographs of Anthony, 1965-2000 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5877)
  - Photographs of Anthony with friends and colleagues, 1987-1998 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5877)
- Recorded Lecture and Announcements of Slide Talks, 1985-1990, undated, Series 9:; (Box 2; 1 folder)
  This file contains an undated 21-minute audio cassette of one of Anthony's slide talk lectures and announcements for other talks.
  - Recorded Lecture and Announcements, 1985-1990 (Box 2 (hol), Reel 5877)